时间索引：03:15 - 翻转机动是怎么工作的，06:00 - 为什么机腹向下 / 终端速度，13:15 - 推重比 / 发动机节流，
21:00 - 重力损失 / 重力拖拽，26:25 - 为什么翻转得这么晚，33:45 - Starship载人安全吗，39:30 - 总结
- Hi, it's me, Tim Dodd, the everyday astronaut.
- 嗨 是我 Tim Dodd 每日宇航员
SpaceX is trying some pretty, crazy things with their Starship rocket.
SpaceX正在用他们的Starship火箭尝试一些相当疯狂的事情
But perhaps there's nothing more crazy
但最疯狂的也许是
原视频名：Why does Starship belly flop
原作者名：Everyday Astronaut
视频来源：youtu.be/BqJ5bKuApbs
原视频发布日期：20210423
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
than letting your nine meter wide, 50 meter tall rocket fall out of the sky, belly first.
让你的9米宽 50米高的火箭以机腹朝前的姿态从天而降
And then try to light your engines basically very last moment,
然后在最后一刻尝试点燃你的发动机
in order to go from horizontal to vertical, to hopefully land softly.
以便从水平方向转为垂直方向 并希望可以软着陆
Now, the reason they're doing this is so they can make their terminal velocity as slow as possible,
现在 他们这样做的原因是 可以让终端速度尽可能地低
so the rocket engines don't have to do nearly as much work slowing the rocket down.
这样发动机不必做那么多工作来减缓火箭的速度
Now, in order to understand what exactly that all means,
那么 为了理解这一切到底意味着什么
there's a ton of physics lessons to unpack here.
就需要学习大量的物理学课程
And seeing all of these spectacular failures,
而在看到所有这些壮观的失败之后
has brought up a lot of really good questions from you guys.
你们提出了很多真正的好问题
But perhaps there's no bigger question than why.
但最大的问题也许是为什么
Why are they doing that belly flop maneuver?
他们为什么要做这种机腹向下的机动？
Why are they going from belly first and then flipping to tail down?
为什么他们要从机腹朝前 翻转到机尾朝下？
And why are they doing that maneuver so late?
而且他们为什么这么晚才做这个机动？
Why don't they just start that landing and maneuver just a little bit earlier,
他们为什么不早一点开始着陆和机动呢？
to make sure there's enough time to make corrections, if something doesn't go right?
这样如果出问题了 还有足够的时间来纠正
But we're also going to look at
但我们也要看看
what other options and constraints and variables SpaceX has with running on different number of engines.
SpaceX使用不同数量发动机点火的情况有多少选择 限制和变量
Is running on more engines better?
用更多的发动机点火是否更好？
Is starting that landing burn earlier better?
更早开始着陆点火是否更好？
And can they use parachutes as a backup, if something goes wrong?
同时如果出现问题 他们能否使用降落伞作为备份？
And of course, we'll answer the ultimate question.
当然 我们将回答一个终极问题
Will this belly flop maneuver ever be safe enough for humans?
这种机腹向下的机动对载人来说是否足够安全？
I mean, could you even survive the G-forces of that crazy flip?
我是指 你甚至能在这样疯狂翻转的过载力下生存吗？
Should SpaceX just scrap this whole idea
SpaceX是否应该放弃这整个想法
and go back to landing at more like a Falcon 9, which has proven to be highly successful.
回到更像已被证明是非常成功的猎鹰9号的着陆方式
So today we're going to cover the wonders of terminal velocity, thrust to weight ratio,
因此 今天我们将讨论终端速度 推重比
gravity drag and engine throttling,
重力拖拽和发动机节流
to see if we can figure out why SpaceX is pursuing such a crazy landing maneuver.
看看我们是否能弄清楚为什么SpaceX要追求如此疯狂的着陆机动
And if we even think that's a good idea or if maybe they should just go back to the drawing board.
以及我们是否认为这是一个好主意 或者也许他们应该重新开始
Let's get started.
那么让我们开始吧
- [Mission Control] Three, two, one,
-  [任务控制]三 二 一
and liftoff!
起飞
- [Neil] That's one small step for man.
-  [尼尔]这是对人类的一小步
- [Mission Control] That's Houston contact for the test one.
-  [任务控制]这是休斯敦和一号测试的通信
Now, right off the bat in case you haven't watched it already,
现在 马上说下 如果你还没有看过的话
youtu.be/-8p2JDTd13k，b23.tv/av885326896
you might want to watch my complete guide to Starship,
你可能想看看我的Starship完全指南
as we actually go over a lot of things that are going to be talked about in this video.
因为我们实际上讨论了很多将在这个视频中谈到的事情
So it might be helpful if you haven't seen that.
所以如果你没有看过 可能会有帮助
Or if you have other questions about Starship in general after you watched this video,
或者如果你看了这个视频后对Starship有其他问题
give that one a watch, it'll likely help you find some answers.
看一下那段视频 它可能会帮助你找到一些答案
But the point of this video is to explain the physics behind the rocket science,
但这个视频的重点是解释火箭科学背后的物理学
not to try and speculate but we're going to help you understand why.
而不是尝试和猜测 但我们要帮助你了解原因
So when SpaceX does make changes, which they inevitably will,
那么 当SpaceX确实不得不做出改变时
you'll have some grasp on why they may have made those decisions.
你就会对他们可能做出这些决定的原因有一些把握
But this is a long video.
但这是一个长视频
And like all my long videos,
和我所有的长视频一样
时间索引：03:15 - 翻转机动是怎么工作的，06:00 - 为什么机腹向下 / 终端速度，13:15 - 推重比 / 发动机节流，
21:00 - 重力损失 / 重力拖拽，26:25 - 为什么翻转得这么晚，33:45 - Starship载人安全吗，39:30 - 总结
we've got some timestamps for you guys for easy watching
我们已经为你们准备了一些时间戳 方便你们观看
or quick skipping to these certain sections you might want to see.
或快速跳到你可能想看的这些特定部分
We also have the YouTube play bar broken up in those same sections.
我们也在YouTube播放条上分割了章节
everydayastronaut.com/starships-belly-flop-maneuver/
And we have an article version of this video up on our website at everydayastronaut.com.
同时在我们的网站everydayastronaut.com上有这个视频的文章版本
The link's in the description so that you can quickly search for certain topics.
链接在视频简介中 以便你可以快速搜索某些主题
[bright music]
[欢快的音乐]
翻转机动是怎么工作的
Starship is doing something completely unique here, with this landing maneuver.
Starship的着陆机动是完全独特的
So, here is how it works or I guess how it's supposed to work.
那么 这是它的工作原理 或者说我认为的它的工作原理
Starship reenters and falls out of the sky belly first,
Starship再入大气并从天空中以机腹朝前的姿态落下
to scrub off as much velocity as possible while falling.
以便在下降过程中尽可能多地消除速度
At about 500m in altitude, it lights up it's Raptor engines, gimbals them full tilt,
在大约500米的高度上 它点燃了猛禽发动机 并使之完全摆动
folds in the rear flaps and swings from horizontal to vertical,
折叠后部翼面 从水平方向旋转到垂直方向
so it can land tail down.
这样它就可以尾部向下着陆
By having the rear fins or Aft fins or as I might call them Elonerons tuck in
通过让尾部翼面或者后部翼面 或者我可以称之为马翼龙的收起
and by keeping the nose fins extended,
并保持鼻锥翼面的伸展
it makes it so the nose has much more drag and will want to point up and the tail will want to fall down,
就使得机头有更大的阻力 并期望可以指向上方 而机尾则落下
which will help to aid in the rotation.
而这将有助于帮助旋转
In later versions of Starship, we'll likely see powerful hot gas thrusters, that could aid in this flip.
在以后的Starship版本中 可能会看到可以帮助这种翻转的 更强大的热气推进器
But as of the making of this video, they've been using purely cold gas thrusters, basically off of a Falcon 9.
但在制作这段视频时 他们一直在使用 基本上是来自猎鹰9号的完全的冷气推进器
But they only use that to get into the belly flop for this testing period
但他们真的只是用它来进入这个测试阶段的机腹向下机动
but they don't actually aid in the flip itself.
但它们实际上并不帮助(从机腹向下到机尾向下的)翻转
Because the rocket is lighting its engines while horizontal,
因为火箭在水平状态下点燃其发动机
it needs to pull propellant from special tanks called header tanks,
它需要从特殊的储罐中抽取推进剂 这些储罐被称为头部储罐
so that the engines don't suck up gas bubbles.
这样发动机就不会吸进气泡
Because of course the main drain valves on a rocket's propellant tank are usually at the bottom of the tank
当然 火箭推进剂箱上的主要排液阀通常在箱体底部
which for a normal rocket is typically oriented point end up, flaming end down.
对于普通的火箭来说 通常是头部朝上 火焰朝下
While Starship is falling through the atmosphere, the propellant will settle on the belly side of the rocket,
当Starship在大气层中下落时 推进剂会沉淀在火箭的腹侧
otherwise known as the Windward side.
也就是所谓的迎风面
Now Starship has these special header tanks, that are essentially just reserve propellant
那么Starship有这些特殊的头部储罐 本质上就是为了储备(可用的)推进剂
that are nearly full and have their drain valve at a little bit of an angle,
它几乎是满的 而且排液阀有一点小的角度
which is perfect for the landing maneuver.
这对于着陆机动来说是完美的
But also because the rocket lights its engines while it's horizontal,
但也因为火箭在水平状态下点燃它的发动机
it'll inject a lot of horizontal velocity and then intentionally over rotate,
它将注入大量的水平速度 然后有意地过度旋转
all the way beyond vertical in the opposite direction, to cancel out that horizontal velocity.
直到超过垂直方向 以抵消水平速度
Once it begins to rotate back to vertical,
一旦它开始旋转回垂直方向
it tucks in its top flaps and will precisely control itself down to a nice soft touchdown,
它就会收起顶部的翼面 并精确地控制并进行一个漂亮的软着陆
much more like a Falcon 9 booster landing.
(这部分)更像是猎鹰9号的助推器着陆
So for now I think we need to answer the most burning question, why.
因此 现在我认为我们需要回答一个最紧迫的问题 即为什么
Why are they even doing this absurd maneuver and not just landing like a Falcon 9,
为什么他们要做这种荒谬的机动 而不是像猎鹰9号那样着陆
since that obviously works, really well?
因为那显然很有效？
[bright music]
[欢快的音乐]
为什么机腹向下？
[终端速度]
- Okay, so let's start with the belly flop maneuver.
- 好吧 让我们从机腹向下的机动开始
Well, like we mentioned at the top of this video and in our complete guide to Starship,
恩 就像我们在这个视频的开头和我们的Starship完全指南 中提到的那样
it's all about scrubbing off as much velocity as possible.
这个机动是为了尽可能多地消除速度
Let the atmosphere do as much work as it can, essentially for free, no propellant necessary.
尽可能多地白用 大气层的工作 这样不需要推进剂就能减速
But one of the biggest reasons that Starship will be coming in belly first
但是Starship会以机腹朝前的姿态再入的最大原因之一
is actually to control peak temperatures and orientation of Starship during orbital re-entry
实际上是为了控制轨道级再入时 其姿态和机身上的峰值温度
which is a huge deal, especially when trying to land at a precise location on Earth or Mars.
这是一个巨大的问题 特别是如果Starship想要精确地着陆在地球或火星的特定位置时
Now we're not going to be focusing on that orbital re-entry portion in today's video
那么我们不打算在今天的视频中重点讨论轨道再入的部分
youtu.be/SCCw_M8MAU0
because I've covered it a bit in some other videos.
因为我已经在其他一些视频中介绍过了
So let's try and figure out
因此 让我们试着弄清楚
why Starship continues to belly flop once it's in the lower portions of the atmosphere,
为什么Starship在进入低层大气后会继续保持机腹向下
when it could easily straighten itself out at a higher altitude and land more like a Falcon 9.
而它可以很容易地在更高的高度上将自己拉直 并像猎鹰9号一样着陆
So the key here is getting your terminal velocity as slow as possible.
那么 这里的关键是让你的终端速度尽可能地低
Terminal velocity is the maximum velocity an object reaches while falling through a fluid such as air.
终端速度是一个物体在通过流体如空气时达到的最大速度
Yes, air is a fluid.
是的 空气是一种流体
It's when the downward force of gravity equals the force of drag.
它是重力的向下作用力等于(空气)阻力时的速度
So the more drag an object has, the slower it's terminal velocity.
因此 一个物体的阻力越大 它的终端速度就越低
It's the same reason why a feather will fall slower than a hammer.
这也是羽毛会比锤子下落得慢的原因
Well, at least here in Earth's atmosphere.
恩 至少在地球的大气层中是这样
- And I'll drop the two of them here and hopefully they'll hit the ground at the same time.
- 我会把它们两个扔在这里 希望它们能同时落地
How about that?
这样如何呢？
- Now, of course, terminal velocity actually changes based on local conditions.
- 那么 当然 终端速度实际上是根据周围环境而变化的
As the atmosphere gets thicker and thicker, drag gets higher,
随着大气层越来越厚 阻力也越来越大
so the terminal velocity is slower and slower.
所以终端速度会越来越低
But as long as your drag is equal to gravity, you are at terminal velocity,
但只要你的阻力与重力相等 你就处于终端速度
even when that velocity number is changing.
即使这个速度数值在变化
Just like skydiving, if you fall belly first, your terminal velocity is at a minimum
就像跳伞一样 如果你腹部朝前 你的终端速度是最小的
and you can spend as much time falling as possible,
而这样你下降的时间就尽可能地多
while also maintaining a lot of control with your arms and legs.
同时还能保持对手臂和腿部的大量控制
Now, imagine if you were skydiving feet or head first, you'd fall substantially faster
那么 想象一下 如果你是脚或头朝前地跳伞 你的下落速度会大大加快
because the oncoming air has much less surface area to hit and slow you down, compared to belly first.
因为比起腹部朝前 头或脚朝前会有更少的表面积来遇到可供减速的空气
So the atmosphere can't do as much work and your terminal velocity would be much higher.
因此 大气层不能做那么多的工作 而你的终端速度会高得多
And if we just look at the belly of Starship versus looking at the bottom of Starship,
而如果我们只是看一下Starship的机腹对比其尾部
you can see just how much more cross section there is.
你就可以看到它的横截面有多大
There's approximately 545 square meters of surface area on the belly side
机腹大约有545平方米的表面积
but only about 70 square meters of surface area on the base of the rocket.
但在火箭的底部只有大约70平方米的表面积
That's 7.8 times more surface area to help slow the rocket down.
这样 帮助火箭减速的表面积就有7.8倍之多
Of course the mass would be the same, no matter the orientation.
当然 无论方向如何 质量都是一样的
So if you have 7.8 times more surface area,
所以如果你有7.8倍的表面积
there's a lot more surface for all the air to push against.
就会有更多的表面让空气来推动
All things considered equal, the terminal velocity will be substantially slower.
如果其他变量一致 那么终端速度将大大降低
Now granted the actual coefficient of drag
那么即使考虑到实际的阻力系数
is vastly different between the concave engine section and the rounded cylindrical body of the rocket.
在凹陷的发动机部分和火箭的圆形圆柱体之间有很大的不同
But even so the terminal velocity is substantially slower falling belly first.
但即使如此 机尾朝前的终端速度也会大大慢于机腹朝前
But perhaps one of the most fun things about using Starship as an example of terminal velocity
但是 用Starship作为终端速度的例子 也许最有趣的一点
is they can actually change its terminal velocity, based on how deployed all of its flaps are.
是他们实际上可以用其翼面来改变它的终端速度
While belly flopping, if Starship deployed all of its flaps out more,
在机腹向下的时候 如果Starship把所有的翼面都展开得更多
it's terminal velocity would be slower because it has more drag.
它的终端速度就会变慢 因为它的阻力更大
If it were to tuck its flaps in a little more,
如果它把翼面收得更紧一点
it's drag would decrease and it would fall faster through the atmosphere with a higher terminal velocity.
它的阻力就会减少 它就会以更高的终端速度在大气层中快速下落
Now in general SpaceX doesn't want the flaps to be maxed out,
那么 一般来说 SpaceX并不希望翼面达到最大
so either all the way open or all the way closed.
也就是要么全部打开 要么全部关闭
Because they would be incapable of making further adjustments to maintain orientation and control.
因为这样就没有能力进行进一步的调整以保持对姿态的控制
So they will likely want to be roughly in the middle remaining relatively neutral.
所以他们可能希望翼面大致保持在中间位置 保持相对中立
And we can actually see the difference of velocity in the telemetry of Starship versus a Falcon 9.
而我们实际上也可以在Starship与猎鹰9号的遥测数据中看到速度的差异
Let's take a look at Declan Murphy's awesome Flight Club data of the two.
让我们来看看Declan Murphy的超强Flight Club对这两者数据的记录
This is a highly accurate simulation of Starship SN8's flight profile and the NROL-108 Falcon 9 mission.
这是对Starship SN8和NROL-108猎鹰9号任务飞行轨迹的高精度模拟
For these initial medium altitude tests like we've been seeing,
对于我们看到的这些最初的类似的中等高度测试
Starship free falls a bit after it gets into the belly flop.
Starship在进入机腹向下姿态后自由落体了一段时间
It slows down as it gets lower and lower and into thicker parts of the atmosphere,
当它越来越低 进入大气层较厚的部分时 它的速度会降低
until it slows all the way down to only about 90 meters per second,
直到它降低到只有大约90m/s
before lighting its engines for the flip and landing burn.
然后再进行翻转和着陆点火
Now, of course, if Starship was falling from a higher altitude or coming back in from orbit,
现在 当然 如果Starship从更高的高度坠落或者从轨道上返回
there would be a higher peak velocity.
会有一个更高的峰值速度
But once it gets into low altitudes and in thicker atmosphere,
但是 一旦它进入低空和较厚的大气层
it should reach terminal velocity, which is very low by the time it lights its engines.
它应该会达到终端速度 也就是在它点燃发动机的时候 它的速度会非常低
And that is great.
而这是很好的
So now let's look at the Falcon 9.
那么现在让我们看看猎鹰9号
Notice that after the entry burn, the Falcon 9 is back in freefall.
请注意 在再入点火后 猎鹰9号回到了自由落体状态
It actually speeds up a little after engine shutdown
实际上 在发动机关闭后 它的速度还加快了一些
because the atmosphere is still pretty thin at 40 kilometers.
因为大气层在40公里处仍然相当稀薄
But then it slows down more and more.
但随后它的速度越来越低
And the more the rocket gets into the lower parts of the atmosphere, the slower it gets.
而且当火箭越深入大气层的较低部分时 它的速度就越慢
And don't forget, Starship won't ever need to do any kind of re-entry burn after its deorbit burn at all,
而且别忘了 Starship在离轨点火后根本不需要做任何形式的再入点火
because it will use its heat shield to protect itself during re-entry
因为它将在再入大气层时使用其热防护罩来保护自己
and the entire broad side of the vehicle to slow down.
同时使用整个航天器的宽阔侧面来减速
So despite coming in at orbital speeds, and not just suborbital speeds like the Falcon 9,
因此 尽管以轨道速度再入 而不是像猎鹰9号那样以亚轨道速度再入
it will only have to do one landing burn.
它将只需要做一次着陆点火
And that right there is a substantial difference.
而这就是一个实质性的区别
But even for the final landing burn,
但是 即使是最后一次着陆点火
staying in the belly flop as long as possible, still pays off.
尽可能长时间地停留在机腹向下的姿态 仍然会有回报
Because notice right before the Falcon 9 lights its engines,
因为注意到在猎鹰9号点燃它的发动机之前
it's velocity is still about 310 meters per second.
它的速度仍然是310m/s左右
That's a little more than three times faster than Starship, before it lights it's engines for the landing burn.
这比Starship在点燃发动机着陆前的速度要快三倍多一点
And it still hasn't even reached the equilibrium of terminal velocity.
而且它甚至还没有达到终端速度的平衡状态
Because at this point it's still experiencing aerodynamic drag of almost two Gs.
因为在此处 它仍然经历着近两个G的空气阻力
So it didn't even reach terminal velocity period.
所以它甚至真的没有达到终端速度
So I guess that's maybe a huge difference,
那么我想这也许是一个巨大的区别
is that Starship will actually hit terminal velocity and the Falcon 9 just doesn't.
也就是Starship将真正达到终端速度 而猎鹰9号却没有
Okay, well, so what?
好吧 那又怎样？
220 meters per second difference?
220m/s的差异？
That doesn't sound like that big of a deal.
这听起来并不是什么大问题
I mean, to get into low Earth orbit,
我是指 要进入低地球轨道
you need to go about 7,800 meters per second.
你需要达到7800m/s
So 220 meters per second, that's only a small fraction of orbital velocity.
那么220m/s 这只是轨道速度的一小部分
Why is this belly flop maneuver worth it?
为什么这种机腹向下的机动是值得的？
Well, here's the problem.
恩 问题是这样的
When you're falling, every second you're trying to slow down propulsively,
当你(垂直)落下(并启动发动机)时 每一秒你都在试图用推力减速
the first 9.8 meters per second of deceleration are just wasted fighting gravity.
而有9.8m/s²的加速度 只是为了对抗重力而浪费掉了
So that 235 meters per second can actually be a lot more
因此 那需要减掉的235m/s实际上可能要多得多
because of something called gravity drag or gravity loss.
因为有一种叫做重力拖拽或重力损失的东西
But in order to actually understand gravity losses,
但为了真正理解重力损失
we need to first explain thrust to weight ratios and engine throttling.
我们需要首先解释推重比和发动机节流这两件事
And here's where the fun begins.
有趣的事情就在这里开始
[bright music]
[欢快的音乐]
推重比 / 发动机节流
Thrust to weight ratio.
推力和重量比
Perhaps you've heard of it,
也许你已经听说过它
perhaps you've played lots of Kerbal space program like me and you have a pretty decent grasp of it.
也许你像我一样玩过很多次坎巴拉太空计划 而对它有一个相当不错的掌握
Or maybe you don't have any idea what I'm talking about at all.
或者 也许你根本不知道我在说什么
And that's fine.
那也没关系
So let's imagine a rocket hovering.
那么 让我们想象一个火箭在悬停
For now, let's completely ignore the atmosphere.
现在 让我们完全忽略大气层
If we separate these forces and concepts, it's going to make this a lot easier to learn.
如果我们把这些力和概念分开 这将使我们更容易学习
So in order to hover, the rocket engine needs to produce exactly as much thrust as the rocket weighs.
所以为了悬停 火箭发动机需要产生与火箭重量完全相同的推力
And in order to explain this best,
为了最好地解释这一点
we're going to use Newtons for both the weight and the thrust of the rocket,
我们要用牛顿(N)来表示火箭的重量和推力
since it's a unit of force.
因为它是一个力的单位
An object with a mass of one kilogram weighs 9.8 Newtons on Earth.
一个质量为1千克(kg)的物体在地球上的重量为9.8牛(N)
This is because Earth's gravity pulls at one kilogram with a force of 9.8 Newtons.
这是因为地球的重力以9.8N的力量拉扯着1kg
And just for fun on Mars, the same mass would weigh 3.7 Newtons.
那么只是为了好玩 在火星上 同样的质量会有3.7N的重量
Of course, it'd be just as easy to use pounds and pounds force in this example
当然 在这个例子中 使用磅和磅力也很简单
but we'll use Newtons despite me not being very used to it but it's all relative anyway.
但我们将使用N 尽管我不太习惯 但这都是相对的
So if your rocket weighs 1000 Newtons,
所以 如果你的火箭重达1000N
otherwise known as they kiloNewton and you're producing 1000 Newtons of thrust in the opposite direction,
也就是所谓的kN 而你在反方向产生1000N的推力
you would hover because you have a thrust to weight ratio of 1:1,
你就会悬停 因为你的推力与重量之比为1:1
which means your thrust is exactly counteracting gravity and therefore your weight.
这意味着你的推力正好抵消了重力 从而抵消了你的重量
So your net acceleration is zero because your thrust is exactly counteracting Earth's pole on your rocket.
所以你的净加速度为零 因为你的推力正好抵消了地球对你的火箭的作用力
Produce 900 Newtons of thrust with your 1000N rocket and your thrust to weight ratio will be less than 1:1,
用你的1000N的火箭产生900N的推力 你的推力与重量比将小于1:1
specifically 0.9:1 and you'll go down.
具体来说是0.9:1 这样你就会下降
For each second you're at this throttle setting with that thrust to weight ratio of 0.9:1,
在这个节流阀设置下 推重比为0.9:1的情况下 每过一秒
you'll go downward faster and faster.
你向下的速度就会越来越高
You'd be accelerating downward.
也就是加速向下
And if you throttle back up to 1:1, you wouldn't go back to a hover magically.
而如果你把油门调高到1:1 你不会神奇地回到悬停状态
You'd actually continue to go down at the same velocity.
而实际上会继续以同样的速度下降
A thrust to weight ratio of 1:1, just means your velocity is not changing.
推重比为1:1 只是意味着你的速度没有变化
So in order to get back to a hover,
因此 为了回到悬停状态
we need to increase our thrust to weight ratio to over 1:1,
我们需要将推重比提高到1:1以上
just to accelerate enough to reach zero velocity.
以达到足够的加速度(去减速) 来达到零速度
So now let's throttle our engines to produce 1,100N of thrust,
因此 现在让我们提高发动机的节流程度 使其产生1,100N的推力
which would be a thrust to weight ratio of 1.1:1 and we'll start canceling out the velocity.
这样 推重比为1.1:1 我们将开始抵消速度
Once we get back to zero velocity, we can return to a thrust to weight ratio of 1:1, if we want to hover.
一旦我们回到零速度 我们就可以回到1:1的推重比 如果我们想悬停
So now let's get back to where we started.
那么现在让我们回到我们开始的地方
Let's go to thrust to weight ratio of 1.5:1 and accelerate quickly upwards.
让我们进入推重比为1.5:1的状态 并迅速向上加速
And again, this is very important to remember,
再说一遍 这一点是非常重要的 要记住
if you instantly throttled back to a thrust to weight ratio of 1:1,
如果你立即将推重比调回1:1
you would continue going up at the same velocity.
你会继续以同样的速度上升
You wouldn't magically hover.
你不会神奇地悬停
So to get back to hovering where we started,
因此 为了回到我们开始时的悬停状态
we'll hold our upwards velocity until we are close to where we started.
我们将保持我们的上升速度 直到我们接近我们开始的地方
And then we'll reduce our thrust to weight ratio below 1:1,
然后 我们将把推重比降低到1:1以下
decelerate until our velocity is at zero meters per second
减速 直到我们的速度为零
and then increase our throttle back to a thrust to weight ratio of 1:1,
然后再把油门加大到推重比为1:1
to maintain a hover right back where we started.
以保持悬停 回到我们开始的地方
It's actually quite hard to make a rocket hover and maneuver
实际上 要使火箭悬停和机动是很难的
but it gets even more complicated
但更复杂的是
when you remember that when a rocket engine is running, it's also burning fuel.
当你想起火箭发动机在运行时 它的燃料也在燃烧
So the rocket is getting lighter and lighter as propellant is expelled.
因此 随着推进剂的排出 火箭变得越来越轻了
So in order to maintain a thrust to weight ratio of say 1:1,
那么 为了保持推重比为1:1
you have to be able to precisely throttle your engine to produce exactly as much thrust as your rocket weighs,
你必须能够精确地控制发动机的节流阀 使其产生的推力与火箭的重量完全相同
even though it's getting lighter and lighter.
即使它变得越来越轻
And of course throttling an engine is a big deal for landing.
但当然 发动机节流对于着陆来说也是一件大事
Otherwise, if you couldn't throttle, you'd have to turn on your engines at the exact right moment.
否则 如果你不能节流 你就必须在准确的时刻打开你的发动机
Huh? That sounds like a really bad idea, right Joe Barnard?
恩？这听起来像是一个非常糟糕的主意 对吗 Joe Barnard？
Okay, so let's take a look at Joe Barnard,
好吧 那么让我们来看看Joe Barnard
from BPS Space's model rocket landing attempts,
在BPS.space模型火箭着陆的尝试中
which he tried to do exactly this by using solid rocket motors,
试图通过使用固体火箭发动机来做到这一点
which can't throttle or shut down early.
而且是不能节流或关机的固体火箭
If you start your landing burn too early and have too much thrust
如果你过早地开始你的着陆点火 并且有太多的推力
and you hit zero velocity above the ground and the engine is still running,
而在具有一定高度时 发动机仍在运转
you're going to go back up.
你就会升回去
[rocket sound]
[火箭声]
If you start your landing burn too late,
如果你的着陆点火开始得太晚
you're not going to be able to scrub off all your velocity and time
你将没有足够的时间来消除所有的速度
and you'll smack into the ground.
然后就会撞上地面
Or if you're like Joe Bernard's rockets,
或者 如果会像Joe Barnard的火箭那样
you're going to turn into a beautiful land shark.
变成一条美丽的陆地鲨鱼
Or here's another fun example.
或者这里还有另一个有趣的例子
The Falcon 9 has too much thrust
猎鹰9号的推力太大
with only one of its nine Merlin engines at minimum throttle to be able to hover.
即使它的九台梅林发动机中只有一台处于最小节流状态 也无法悬停
So they have to start the landing burn very precisely.
所以他们必须非常精确地启动着陆点火
This is called doing a hover slam or a suicide burn.
这被称为进行一次悬停式撞击或自杀式点火
If SpaceX started too early, they could run the risk of running out of fuel
如果SpaceX开始得太早 他们可能会有燃料耗尽的风险
or hitting zero velocity before they touched the ground and would fall from even higher altitude.
或在他们接触地面之前达到零速度 甚至从更高的高度坠落
And of course if the Falcon 9 starts its engines too late, it will engage in an unscheduled disassembly,
而当然 如果猎鹰9号发动机启动得太晚 它将发生意外解体
这里的梗是Millennium Falcon(千年隼)，也是猎鹰9号的命名来源
when it hits the ground at a very high velocity turning it into a Falcon million pieces.
此时 它会以非常高的速度撞向地面 变成百万猎鹰碎片
Since a single Merlin engine can throttle between 100% down to about 40%,
由于单台梅林发动机可以在100%到40%之间节流
you can start your landing burn at a point where your throttle is directly in between the two,
你可以让节流阀在这个范围内开始着陆点火
so about 70%.
那么大约是70%
This allows you to increase your throttle, if you started a little late
这样 如果你点火时间稍晚 就可以增加节流程度以进行调整
or decrease your throttle, if you started a little early.
或者如果点火时间稍早 则可以减少节流程度
The rocket is continually calculating its velocity, it's deceleration
火箭在不断地计算它的速度和减速度
and trying to make it hit zero meters per second, right when it hits zero meters in altitude.
并试图让它在零高度的时候正好达到零速度
It will precisely control its throttle right up until touchdown.
它将精确地控制其节流阀 直到着陆
Although this is all done autonomously by the flight computer,
尽管这些都是由飞行计算机自主完成的
which can precisely calculate exactly how much and how quickly to slow it down,
其可精确地计算出减速度
it isn't quite as scary as you might think.
这并不像你想象的那么可怕
In fact, you may have done this a lot.
事实上 你可能经常这样做
Like maybe every single day.
比如也许每天都有这样做
[bright music]
[欢快的音乐]
A lot of us actually do a hover slam or a suicide burn,
我们很多人实际上做过悬停式撞击或自杀式点火
basically every day if you drive a car.
如果你开车的话 基本上每天都在做
So today we're actually going to be practicing our own hover slams and suicide burns
因此 实际上今天我们将练习我们自己的悬停式撞击或自杀式点火
and showing you that by modulating your brake pedal,
并通过调节刹车踏板来向你展示这种方法
you're basically doing the exact same thing as a rocket engine slowing down.
你基本上是在做与火箭发动机点火减速完全相同的事情
So I'm going to be doing this with my friend Trevor Mahlmann.
所以我将和我的朋友Trevor Mahlmann一起来做这件事
So let's say you're traveling at 50 kilometers per hour and there's a Stop sign ahead.
假设你以50km/h的速度行驶 而前面有一个停止标志
We want to try and stop right at the Stop sign without ever letting off the brakes
我们想试着在停止标志前停下 而不松开刹车踏板
and without ever touching the accelerator pedal again.
同时也不要再碰油门踏板
And this example, the Stop sign is the ground, we're the rocket falling
那么在这个例子中 停车标志是地面 我们是正在下落的火箭
and we're using our brakes as the rocket engine that is slowing us down.
而制动器作为火箭发动机 使我们减速
But we can even go a little bit deeper with this example,
但借助这个例子 我们甚至可以再深入一点
since letting off the accelerator of your car is like lighting up your rocket engine.
因为松开汽车的油门就像点燃了你的火箭发动机
Because you begin to slow down before you even use your brakes.
因为在你还没有使用刹车之前 你就开始减速了
This is called engine braking.
这就是所谓的发动机制动
And although it's pretty obvious in lower gears of an internal combustion engine car,
尽管这个效应在内燃机汽车的低档位上非常明显
it's even more obvious in a hybrid or an electric vehicle, which have regenerative braking.
但它在混合动力汽车或电动车中甚至更加明显 因为它们有再生制动功能
And with the Tesla, we can even change our regenerative breaking setting to be standard or low,
而对于特斯拉 我们甚至可以改变我们的再生制动设置为标准或较低
which would be the same as changing the rocket engines' minimum throttle setting.
这就相当于改变火箭发动机的最小节流阀设置
So the next time you're driving around town,
所以下次你在城里开车时
think about when you let off your accelerator,
想一想你什么时候松开油门
you just lit up your rocket engine, which will start slowing you down.
(就像)你刚刚点燃了你的火箭发动机 而这将使你开始减速
And as you use your brakes, it's like throttling your rocket engine more or less.
而当你使用刹车时 就像或多或少地给你的火箭发动机节流
It's pretty fun.
这很有趣
Okay, so that's thrust to weight ratio and hover slams.
好吧 这就是推重比与悬停式撞击
So how has that affect this gravity drag/gravity loss thing?
那么 这对这个重力拖拽/重力损失的事情有什么影响？
[bright music]
[欢快的音乐]
重力损失
Okay, so what the heck is this gravity drag or gravity loss thing?
好吧 那么这件重力拖拽或重力损失的事情到底是什么？
Gravity loss is when you're using your engine to fight gravity.
重力损失是用你的发动机来对抗重力
So let's assume you have a thrust to weight ratio of 1:1.
因此 让我们假设你的推重比为1:1
As we know, you're not changing your velocity at all, your engines are just fighting gravity.
正如我们所知 你完全没有改变你的速度 你的发动机只是在对抗重力
So every second, you're running your engine with a thrust to weight ratio of 1:1,
所以每一秒钟 你都在以1:1的推重比运行你的发动机
you're just wasting precious propellant fighting gravity.
你只是在浪费宝贵的推进剂来对抗重力
Your engine is trying to accelerate your craft at 9.8 meters per second squared and so is gravity,
发动机正试图以9.8m/s²的加速度加速飞船 而重力也是如此
just in the opposite direction.
只是在相反的方向
Now, like we talked about to actually get somewhere,
那么 就像我们谈到的那样 要真正取得进展
we need a thrust to weight ratio of more than 1:1,
我们需要一个超过1:1的推重比
since the first bit of propellant will always be sacrificed to that pesky gravity.
因为总有一部分推进剂会被牺牲给那讨厌的重力
And this makes a big difference in the overall efficiency and performance of a rocket.
而这对火箭的整体效率和性能有很大的影响
So let's plot this out because it's pretty fun to see spelled out.
因此 让我们把这个问题画出来 因为看到这个问题的答案是非常有趣的
On the left, we'll show thrust to weight ratio versus how much of the propellant is actually performing work,
左边这张图的横坐标是推重比 纵坐标是做功(机械功)的推进剂的比例
which is basically the efficiency of the burn against gravity.
基本上表明了点火对抗重力的效率
On the right, we'll show the thrust to weight ratio versus acceleration.
右边这张图的横坐标是推重比 纵坐标是加速度
So how much net acceleration the rocket is experiencing.
这样就表明了火箭经受的净加速度
If our thrust to weight ratio is 1:1, 100% of our propellant is spent fighting gravity,
如果我们的推重比是1:1 所有的推进剂都是用来对抗重力的
and 0% of our propellant is getting us somewhere,
而没有推进剂是在使我们到达某处
and as you know, that means our net acceleration is zero.
而如你所知 这意味着我们的净加速度为零
If our thrust to weight ratio is 1.1:1,
如果我们的推重比是1.1:1
91% of our propellant is still spent fighting gravity and only 9% is used getting us somewhere,
91%的推进剂仍然用于对抗重力 只有9%的推进剂使我们到达某处
with the net acceleration of 0.1Gs.
而净加速度为0.1G
But this produces infinitely more work than a thrust to weight ratio of 1:1,
但这比推重比为1:1的情况下产生的功要多无穷倍
since that wasn't producing any.
因为那并没有产生任何功
So let's jump up to a thrust to weight ratio of 1.5:1.
那么 让我们跳到1.5:1的推重比
Now two thirds of our propellant is wasted to gravity and one third goes into accelerating the vehicle.
那么 三分之二的推进剂被浪费在重力上 三分之一被用于加速航天器
So although we only increased our thrust 36% over a thrust to weight ratio of 1.1:1,
因此 尽管只比1.1:1的推重比增加了36%的推力
we actually produced five times the amount of net acceleration, getting us to 0.5Gs.
实际上却产生了五倍的净加速度 使之达到了0.5G
Let's do it again now with a thrust to weight ratio of 2:1.
现在让我们再做一次 推重比达到了2:1
Now 50% of our propellant is wasted on gravity and 50% of our propellant goes to accelerating our vehicle.
那么 50%的推进剂被浪费在重力上 50%的推进剂用于加速我们的航天器
Compared to 1.5:1,
与1.5:1相比
we only increased our thrust by 33% but we produced twice the amount of acceleration.
我们只增加了33%的推力 却产生了两倍的加速度
If we have a thrust to weight ratio of 3:1,
如果推重比为3:1
only one third of our propellant was wasted fighting gravity and two thirds was used to perform work.
只有三分之一的推进剂被浪费在对抗重力上 三分之二的推进剂被用于做功
Which is great, so we increase our thrust by 50% and we still doubled our acceleration.
这很好 所以(虽然只)增加了50%的推力 加速度仍然增加了一倍
And lastly, if we have a thrust to weight ratio of 6:1,
最后 如果我们的推重比为6:1
gravity only eats up about 17%.
重力只消耗了大约17%
So again, we doubled our thrust and more than doubled our acceleration.
因此 这样再次把推力增加了一倍 加速度也增加了一倍多
But notice we went from 66% of our propellant producing work at a thrust to weight ratio of 3:1,
但是请注意 推重比为3:1时 66%的推进剂可以用来做功
up to only 83% with a thrust to weight ratio of 6:1.
而到了推重比为6:1时 只有83%的推进剂可以用来做功
So we're definitely seeing some diminishing returns.
因此 收益正在减少
And no matter how high your thrust to weight ratio is,
而且 无论你的推重比有多高
you'll never reach 100% of your propellant performing work
都永远不可能让所有的推进剂拿来做功
because gravity will always eat 9.8 meters per second squared here on Earth.
因为在地球上 重力将永远吃掉9.8m/s²的加速度
But percentage of how much of your thrust gravity is eating, just keeps going down and down
但是 你的推力被重力吃掉的百分比在不断地下降
until it's not really a major factor in the efficiency of your landing burn.
直到它不再主要地影响你的着陆点火效率
So let's think about a Falcon 9 falling from the sky again.
因此 让我们再想一想猎鹰9号从空中坠落的情况
If it's thrust to weight ratio is really low like 1.1:1,
如果它的推重比真的很低 比如1.1:1
it would have to start its landing burn very high up
它将不得不在很高的位置开始其着陆点火
and most of its propellant would be wasted just fighting gravity.
而它的大部分推进剂将被浪费在对抗重力上
It takes substantially more propellant to start your burn this high up.
在这么高的地方开始点火需要大量的推进剂
Or think of it the other way.
或者换个角度想一想
If you had a much higher thrust to weight ratio, it could do a very short landing burn,
如果你有一个更高的推重比 着陆点火可以变得非常短
lighting it's engines at the last second
(甚至只需要)在最后一秒点燃它的发动机
and only a small fraction of the propellant was wasted fighting gravity.
而只有一小部分推进剂在对抗重力时被浪费了
But the reality is it's actually not quite as bad as we just made it seem,
但现实是 (重力损失)实际上并不像我们刚才说的那样糟糕
at least here on Earth with Earth's atmosphere
至少在地球上的话 有地球的大气层
and especially towards the beginning of a Falcon 9's landing burn.
而且特别是在猎鹰9号着陆点火开始之前 (大气层的减速起主要作用)
Now this is really getting into the weeds on all this but when the Falcon 9 is near terminal velocity,
那么 接下来就是真正的细节部分 但当猎鹰9号接近终端速度时
drag alone is already producing an awful lot of deceleration.
仅仅是阻力就已经产生了非常大的减速
There's much more drag than gravity is pulling down on the rocket,
比起重力对火箭的拉扯 阻力要大得多
so it's slowing down before the engines even light.
所以它在发动机点燃之前就已经减速了
But once you light your engines, you of course begin to slow the rocket down
但是一旦你点燃你的发动机 你当然会开始使火箭减速
but ironically, you're actually reducing the drag the rocket experiences.
但具有讽刺意味的是 你实际上也是在减少火箭的阻力(因为速度的下降)
So the slower the rocket engine makes the rocket, the more work it actually has to do to fight off gravity.
因此 火箭发动机使火箭的速度越慢 为了对抗重力 它实际要做的功就越多
Near the end of the landing burn, it's basically carrying all the weight of the rocket
在着陆点火接近尾声时 它基本上承担了火箭的所有重量
and our whole thrust to weight ratio thing really matters here the most.
而前面所探讨的推重比的事情 在这里(才)是最重要的
It's honestly crazy to me that
老实说 这对我来说很疯狂
engineers have to factor in all of this stuff, when they're designing these landing profiles.
在工程师们设计这些着陆轨迹 考虑所有的这些事情的时候
Okay, so now we know about terminal velocity.
好了 现在我们知道了终端速度
We know about gravity drag and how a high thrust to weight ratio can help combat it.
我们知道了重力拖拽 以及高推重比是如何帮忙应对它的
I think it's time we get into
我想现在是时候让我们了解
why does SpaceX do the flip from belly flop to tail down, so late?
为什么SpaceX从机腹向下到机尾向下的翻转机动来得这么晚？
[bright music]
[欢快的音乐]
为什么翻转得这么晚？
So we finally have all the pieces of knowledge necessary to explain
因此 我们终于有了所有必要的知识片段来解释
why they want to do the flip pretty much as late as possible.
为什么他们要尽可能晚地做翻转
As you know, the terminal velocity of going belly first is much slower than engines down.
正如你所知道的 机腹朝前的终端速度要比发动机向下慢得多
So the longer they in that belly flop position, the less work the engines have to do.
因此 处在机腹向下的姿态的时间越长 发动机要做的功就越少
Cool, easy, but next we actually have a very carefully planned and wonderful compromise of mission planning.
很酷 很简单 但接下来我们实际上做了一个非常精心策划的 美妙的任务规划的妥协
Every decision has a compromise.
每个决定都包含妥协
So here's where things get pretty fun.
所以这里是事情变得相当有趣的地方
So let's make an assumption.
所以让我们做一个假设
We want to be belly flopping for as long as possible to scrub off velocity.
我们想在尽可能长的时间内保持机腹向下的姿态 以消除速度
But we also want to land safely and reliably, right?
但我们也想安全 可靠地着陆 对吗？
So we do want some wiggle room there
所以我们确实希望有一些回旋的余地
and not be doing this last second landing burn, where there's absolutely no margin for error.
而不是在最后一秒做着陆点火 那样绝对没有出错的余地
What options are there?
有哪些选择呢？
Starship has three sea-level Raptor engines,
Starship有三台海平面猛禽发动机
all capable of aiding and the landing flip and landing burn.
都能够帮助着陆翻转和着陆点火
Each engine can throttle between about 40% and 100% throttle setting.
每台发动机可以在大约40%和100%的节流设置之间进行节流
So we can actually have some crossovers and thrust options,
所以实际上有一些点火组合的总推力是相同的
if we're running on one engine, two engines or three engines.
如果我们用一台 两台 三台发动机运行
With one engine running, we can produce between approximately 880 kN to 2200 kN of thrust.
在一台发动机运行时 可以产生大约880kN至2200kN的推力
With two engines running, we can produce between 1,760 kN to 4,400 kN of thrust.
两台发动机运行时 可以产生1760kN至4400kN的推力
And with three engines running, we can produce 2,640 kN to 6,600 kN of thrust.
而在三台发动机运行时 可以产生2640kN至6600kN的推力
And a good point of reference here,
这里还有一个很好的参考点
when Starship is falling from the sky before it lights its engines,
当Starship在点燃它的发动机之前从空中坠落时
it weighs approximately 1.4 million Newtons,
它的重量大约为140万牛
otherwise known as 1.4 mega Newtons or 1400 kN.
又称1.4MN或1400kN
That's about one mega Newton of weight for a dry Starship
Starship的干质量大概为1MN
and about 400 kN worth of weight for the propellant that's leftover for landing,
而着陆时剩余的推进剂大约为400kN
with a little bit left over for safety margins.
这些推进剂容量中包括一些安全冗余
Now, of course, these numbers are subject to change, as Starship gets more and more refined.
那么 当然 随着Starship变得越来越完善 这些数字可能会改变
It'll probably get a little bit heavier because it has more our heat shield
Starship可能会变得更重一点 因为有更多的隔热板
but we could see the header tank shrink or whatever.
但也有可能缩水头部储罐来平衡这部分的质量增加之类的
But for now, let's just use this as a reference.
但是现在 仅仅把这个数值作为一个参考
We actually have a ton of engine options here but right away, you may notice.
实际上 发动机(点火)选择很多 但马上 你可能会注意到
we actually have a little bit of a paradox.
我们实际上有一个小的矛盾
If you want to start the flip early, you'll need a low thrust to weight ratio.
如果你想提前启动翻转 你就需要一个低的推重比
So say one engine at a low throttle setting, which is the least reliable thing,
那么假设是使用一台节流的发动机 而这是最不可靠的事情
as if you lose an engine,
因为如果你失去了一台发动机
it may take too long to get the other engines up and running.
可能需要太长的时间才能让其他的发动机启动并运行
But if you want to run all three engines the whole time,
但是 如果你想让三台发动机一直运行下去
you'll have to start the flip scarily late and awfully close to the ground
你将不得不在非常晚的时间才开始翻转 而且要非常接近地面
because with all three engines running at low throttle settings,
因为在三台发动机都以低节流设置运行的情况下
it would still be a pretty aggressive suicide burn.
这仍然会是一个相当激进的自杀式点火(而无法进一步节流而做到悬停)
But SpaceX has the option of lighting all three engines for the flip
但SpaceX可以选择点燃所有三台发动机用于翻转
and then reducing the number of engines running, once the vehicle is closer to the ground,
然后一旦航天器接近地面时 再减少发动机的运行数量
so they can have greater fine throttle control,
这样他们的节流控制就可以更加精确
while maintaining some redundancies at engine ignition,
同时还能在发动机点火时保持一些冗余
which seems like a decent compromise.
这似乎是一个不错的折衷方案
But the performance hit of starting too early is actually quite a big deal.
但过早启动对性能的负面影响实际上是相当大的
In fact, I had Declan Murphy
事实上 我让Declan Murphy
show the differences between the Delta V requirements for your landing burn at two different altitudes.
展示了在两个不同高度上对着陆点火的速度增量(dv)要求之间的差异
And real quick reminder here of what Delta V is.
那么在这里真的快速提示一下什么是dv
It means change in velocity.
它意味着速度的变化
And for rockets, you can kind of think of it like the range of a car.
对于火箭来说 你可以把它看作是汽车的续航能力
It's the balance of the fuel efficiency of your engine and how much fuel you have in your car.
它是发动机的燃料效率和汽车燃料量之间的平衡
So the higher the Delta V you have, the further you can go.
那么你的dv越高 就能走得越远
So about the absolute earliest Starship can flip, is 2.5 kilometers.
因此 Starship可以翻转的绝对最早(大)高度 是2.5km
译者的理解：这里的图应该是指，在不增加着陆质量，持续减速，单次点火，但允许个别发动机关机的情况下，绝对最大高度的值是由初速度(终端速度)和推重比大于1来约束的，
而非燃料质量不足，事实上后文也提到头部储罐里的燃料是足够的，但为了花光那些燃料估计得增加做无用功的部分，或者进行多次发动机点火，转为垂直姿态后关机加速等等
And that's flipping with two engines,
并且这是用两台发动机的翻转
then going down to one engine at nearly minimum throttle setting for the entire landing burn
然后减少到一台发动机 并在整个着陆过程中使用几乎是最小的节流设置
and using basically as much header tank fuel as possible.
并且基本上使用尽可能多的头部储罐燃料
Then about the absolute latest Starship can flip, is down around 300 meters.
那么 Starship能够翻转的绝对最晚(小)高度 低达300米左右
And that requires all three Raptor engines running at their highest throttle setting,
而这需要所有三台猛禽发动机以最高节流设置运行
full bore, pulling 4.5 GS to come to a soft touchdown.
全速推进 拉出4.5个G的过载来实现软着陆
So now between these two options is some reasonable compromise.
所以现在在这两个选项之间的配置是一些合理的妥协
Likely right around the 550 meter mark, like we've seen SpaceX trying the flip so far
可能就在550米左右 就像我们目前看到的SpaceX尝试翻转的情况一样
and this balances some engine out capabilities
而这就对一些发动机失效的情况作了平衡
and allows for some engine overlapping thrust profiles
并允许一些总推力相同的发动机点火配置
and it doesn't have a long and inefficient landing burn.
而且着陆点火也不会那么漫长而低效
Because when you compare their Delta V requirements at each of these altitudes,
因为当你比较这些不同高度的dv要求时
译者的计算：取初质量m₁ = 140t，排气速度vₑ = 3200m/s，使用火箭方程，可根据不同dv计算消耗的燃料质量
实际上，所有的这些配置都没有超过理论上头部储罐能装载的最多燃料质量30t，当然，这里不考虑管路影响，燃料无法用尽的情况
~24.7t燃料质量
~10.5t燃料质量
~6.0t燃料质量
you can see there isn't a huge difference between 550 meters and 300 meters
你就可以看到在550米和300米之间并没有很大的差别
but there is a fairly substantial performance difference, if you start up at 2.5 kilometers.
但如果你在2.5公里处启动 则会有相当大的性能差异
The result of that Delta V savings could be as much as almost 20 tons of propellent,
节省dv的结果可能是节省多达近20吨的推进剂
which could mean slightly more than 20 tons that you could have put into orbit.
而这可能意味着你可以把(另外)20吨多的东西送入轨道(因为是末级)
Which is more than a single Falcon 9 has ever launched into orbit, period.
而这甚至比猎鹰9号目前进行过的单次发射中 入轨的质量还要多
So that's a lot of mass.
那么这是一个很大的质量
But of course it's important to remember for now, with its header tanks nearly full,
但当然 现在重要的是要记住 在头部储罐几乎装满的情况下
it's around 30 tons of fuel anyway.
是可以达到差不多30吨质量的推进剂的
So they might as well use all of it and do whatever is the safest.
所以他们不妨全部使用 并且进行最安全的配置
But maybe in the future, we could see the header tanks shrink as they aim to increase performance,
但也许在未来 我们可以看到头部储罐的缩小 因为他们要提高性能
while still having some redundant options for landing.
同时仍有一些冗余的着陆选择
But 2.5 kilometers is about the earliest Starship can do the flip, period.
但2.5公里大约真的是Starship能做的最早的翻转
译者的理解(这次我比每日宇航员更懂.jpg)：其实应该是如前所说的初速度和推重比大于1的限制，而非燃料量的限制，
如果翻转高度继续提高，为了给后期减速留速度余量，推重比将不得不降到1甚至更低，从而降低效率，延长点火时间，
由于延长了点火时间，某种程度上减少了安全性/可靠性，考虑到到目前为止猛禽发动机的可靠性真的捉急
Due to the size of the header tanks,
由于头部储罐的大小
which again of course, could always change
当然 这也可以随时改变
but then you're just making it more inefficient
但是 (这样对头部储罐的放大)只是让它的效率更低
and not really any more reliable, in any conceivable way if you were flipping earlier.
而如果更早地翻转 想象不出还能带来更多的可靠性(因为发动机点火时间更长)
'Cause let's stop and think about it.
因为让我们停下来想一想
So far of the four Starship prototypes that have flown as of the making of this video,
到目前为止 在制作这段视频时 已经飞行的四枚Starship原型机中
请暂停观看：Starship SN8到SN11事故原因的简略汇总
老八：头部储罐加压问题，即使早翻转可能也无法让别的发动机正常工作
老九：翻转时有一台发动机点火失败，然后又没有补救，实际上是发动机可靠性以及翻转机动时发动机点火程序冗余度不足的问题，
其次才是高度，或者说连冗余度的代码都没有写就更别指望更高的高度做好决策了
老十：推进剂管路问题，当然可能可以通过在更高的高度启动另一台发动机来解决问题
老十一：雾中神奇爆炸，不知道发生了什么，老马说是发动机管路泄漏导致的，也就是发动机可靠性问题
来源：en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SpaceX_Starship#Prototypes
none of them really would have worked out any better, had they started the flip earlier.
即使他们早点开始翻转 也不会获得更好的结果
The exception being maybe SN10,
唯一的例外也许是SN10
which had a problem where it was sucking up some of it's helium instead of propellant,
它的问题是 发动机吸到了一些氦气而不是推进剂
which means the rocket hit the ground at too high of velocity.
导致火箭以过高的速度撞击地面
Now, of course there might always be some missions
那么 当然可能总是有一些任务
that have some unique edge cases or more extreme requirements.
会存在独特的边缘情况或更极端的要求
For instance, a heavier payload during landing,
例如 在着陆时有较重的有效载荷
may always require all three engines running at nearly maximum throttle for landing.
可能总是需要所有三台发动机以几乎最大的节流运行来着陆(以节省燃料)
But that might not be a safe or reliable solution for humans.
但这对载人来说可能不是一个安全或可靠的解决方案
To me, it seems like what they're doing now with lighting up three engines at the flip is great.
对我来说 他们现在所做的在翻转时点燃三台发动机的做法似乎很好
Because that way, if one of them isn't working out okay,
因为这样一来 如果其中一台发动机不正常
they can just continue to do the flip and the landing on two engines.
他们可以继续用两台发动机进行翻转和着陆
Okay, so all of this will allow a Starship to fall slower
好了 所有这些都会让Starship下降得更慢
and when timed correctly, it'll use very little propellant for the landing burn,
而当时间正确时 它在着陆时使用的推进剂会非常少
which will increase the performance of the rocket,
而这将提高火箭的性能
since the propellant saved can be used to put more stuff into orbit.
因为节省下来的推进剂可以用来把更多的东西送入轨道
And that's the whole point.
而这正是问题的关键
So the real goldmine for SpaceX will be finding that exact right altitude
因此 对SpaceX来说 真正的收益将是找到一个准确的高度
that balances performance, engine shutdown opportunities with overlapping thrust options between the engines
以平衡性能 发动机失效(冗余度)和总推力相同的发动机点火配置选择
and leaves them with the fewest chances to make a big old boom.
使得大爆炸的可能变得最小
But aren't big, huge booms inevitable no matter how reliable you make it?
但是 无论你做得多么可靠 大爆炸仍是不可避免的吗？
How is SpaceX actually going to make this reliable enough to make it safe for humans?
SpaceX实际上将如何让Starship变得足够可靠 以用于载人？
Can they?
他们能吗？
[bright music]
[欢快的音乐]
Starship载人安全吗？
Okay, let's say everything works out perfectly and Starship can land reliably.
好吧 让我们假设一切顺利 而Starship可以可靠地着陆
This maneuver still looks pretty intense and isn't it always subject to some spectacular failures?
这种机动看起来仍然相当激烈 但不总会出现一些壮观的失败
What would it be like if humans were on board Starship,
如果Starship载人 会是什么样子
can it be safe?
它能安全吗？
Is this something your life could depend on?
这是你的生命可以依赖的东西吗？
youtu.be/ENLrk1q1l3M
As someone who wants to ride this thing now for Dear Moon, we better get into this.
作为一个现在就想为了亲爱的月球 项目而坐这个东西的人 我们最好进入这个问题
Well, first off, the biggest weakness.
好吧 首先 最大的弱点
We need to remind ourselves that for now, the Raptor engines are still in their infancy.
我们需要提醒自己 就目前而言 猛禽发动机仍处于起步阶段
They're literally still in development and they're getting more reliable by the day.
它们真的仍在开发中 所以正变得越来越可靠
They are far from perfect
(但)离完美还很远
but SpaceX is flying and testing these things at a blistering speed and they're accelerating.
不过SpaceX正在以极快的速度飞行和测试这些发动机 他们正在加速
So with general engine reliability,
因此 随着发动机总体可靠性的提高
the reliability of this maneuver will go up drastically, like we just talked about.
这种机动的可靠性也将大幅提高 如前所述
By having landing profiles that will have few single point failures, it could become much more reliable.
通过几乎没有单点故障的着陆配置 这可以变得更加可靠
And on top of this SpaceX will practice this maneuver a ton,
在此基础上 SpaceX将大量实践这种机动
since they're planning on flying Starship in insane amount,
因为他们正计划以惊人的数量飞行Starship
between cargo and eventually refueling flights and all these other things,
这包括货物型Starship 以及最终要进行的推进剂补加飞行等等
not only in this testing phase but once it's operational, it'll see an awful lot of flights
不仅是在这个测试阶段 一旦它投入使用 就会产生大量的飞行
and they'll have plenty of time to learn from successes, close calls and failures.
而他们将有足够的时间从成功 险情和失败中学习
But there is something that will hopefully help make this flip maneuver itself a little bit more reliable,
但是 还是有一些措施可以使这个翻转机动本身更可靠一些
if there are problems with say the engine gimbaler or something,
比如说 发动机的摆动装置出了问题
because SpaceX is working on powerful, hot gas thrusters,
因为SpaceX正在研究强大的热气推进器
that use high pressure gaseous methane and high pressure gaseous oxygen,
这种推进器使用高压气态甲烷和高压气态氧
that can aid in the flip maneuver.
可以帮助翻转机动
But what if they didn't do that flip at all?
但是 如果他们根本就不做翻转机动呢？
Would the hot gas thrusters be powerful enough to just simply land belly first?
热气推进器的推力是否足以让它们只是简单地以机腹朝前的姿态着陆？
Well, no, the hot gas thrusters will not be nearly powerful enough to be able to actually slow an entire Starship.
恩 不 热气推进器的推力远远不能使整枚Starship减速
But if you had enough of them, of course, you could maybe do that
但是 如果你有足够多的热气推进器 当然 也许可以做到这一点
but lugging around all those additional engines and that extra plumbing,
但拖着所有这些额外的发动机和额外的管道
adds a lot of complexity, a lot more failure points and a lot of weight.
增加了很多的复杂度 故障点和重量
Besides that, they'd have to beef up the rocket to handle landing it horizontally
除此之外 他们还必须加强火箭的强度 以处理水平着陆的(局部承力结构强度)问题
but more importantly, Starship already has Raptor engines,
但更重要的是 Starship已经有了猛禽发动机
which are arguably some of the most incredible rocket engines ever made
这可以说是有史以来最不可思议的火箭发动机了
and will substantially outperform hot gas thrusters in every metric.
而且在每一项性能指标上都会大大超过热气推进器
So why would they want to land on less efficient engines?
所以他们为什么要用效率较低的发动机来着陆呢？
But the same thing is basically true for parachutes.
但对于降落伞来说 基本上也是同样的事情
I have a lot of people asking me why they aren't using parachutes as a backup,
有很多人问我 为什么他们不使用降落伞作为备份
if the main engines didn't light or something like that.
如果主发动机没有点燃之类的话
Well, the first and most obvious reason for parachutes is that they take a long time to deploy.
好吧 降落伞的第一个也是最明显的原因是 它们需要很长的时间来展开
And you have to deploy them in stages,
而且你必须分阶段展开它们
so you don't create too much shock and destroy the chutes and or the lines.
这样就不会产生太大的冲击力而破坏降落伞或线路
If Starship is lighting its engines up at say even 2000 meters
如果Starship在2000米高空点燃了它的发动机
and something goes wrong and they need to then deploy the parachutes,
而出了问题 之后他们需要展开降落伞
坎星黑科技不服，日常1000m开伞
that's not even enough time to deploy the small drogue chutes, let alone the main chutes.
这甚至没有足够的时间来展开较小的引导伞 更不用说主降落伞了
Not to mention the sheer weight of the parachutes and parachute system.
更不用说降落伞和降落伞系统(会增加)的纯粹重量了
They actually weigh quite a bit between the different chutes, the mortars that deploy them
各种不同的降落伞 弹射器实际上都会占用相当大的重量
and of course, again, beefing up the structure,
同时 当然 还需要加强结构
to handle the loads in that orientation and from the parachute mounting points.
以处理该方向和降落伞安装点的载荷
And let's not forget about the sheer mass of Starship.
同时让我们不要忘记Starship的巨大质量
At 100 metric tons when it's dry with absolutely zero fuel on board,
不带燃料的100吨的干质量
it would be the heaviest thing to ever be carried under parachutes.
它将是有史以来用降落伞运载的最重的东西
The previous record was the space shuttle solid rocket boosters, which weighed about 90 tons.
之前的记录是航天飞机的固体火箭助推器 (干质量)重约90吨
That's right, the space shuttle's SRBs were actually the largest parachutes ever.
没错 航天飞机的固体火箭助推器(SRB)实际上是(使用了)有史以来最大的降落伞
And they had three drogue chutes and then there are three main chutes,
那么其中有三个下降伞和三个主伞
which weighed around five tons just for the parachutes.
仅仅是降落伞就重达5吨左右
Again, not to mention the mortars that would fire it
另外 更不用说发射它的弹射器了
or the additional structure for mounting the parachute to.
或用于安装降落伞的额外结构
Okay, forget backups parachutes or backup engines and stuff like that.
好吧 忘了备用降落伞或备用发动机之类的东西
Let's say the flip just becomes 99.99% reliable for landing.
让我们假设 翻转的可靠性确实达到了99.99%
Can a human even withstand the G-forces of the flip maneuver?
那么甚至有人能承受这样的翻转机动的过载力吗？
Well, for that, let's take a look at the peak Gs of the landing maneuver.
好吧 为了这个问题 让我们来看看着陆机动的峰值过载
Believe it or not, the peak Gs of the flip and landing is under three GS.
信不信由你 翻转和着陆的峰值过载低于3G
Now, granted they may be in a slightly dizzying mixture of vertical and horizontal,
那么 得承认在垂直和水平的混合状态下 乘客可能有点眩晕
but they're not even as great as many rollercoasters.
但这样的过载甚至没有许多过山车那么大
And of course there likely could be seats that would rotate
而且 当然 也有可能有可旋转的座椅
and make it so you always experienced G-forces in the same direction,
并使你总是在同一方向上经历过载
mostly lying on your back to spread out the GS as much as possible, to keep you safe.
让你总是背朝下 尽可能地分散过载力 以保证你的安全
And just look at the actual maneuver.
同时再看一下实际的机动
Follow the nose where the passengers or cargo would be someday.
注意那个未来可能载货或载人的机头
It doesn't actually move that much at all.
它实际上根本就没有移动那么多
Yes, the tail whips around pretty aggressively but the nose barely does at all.
是的 机尾摆动的幅度相当大 但机头几乎没有任何机动
I think it just looks scarier than it is.
我认为它只是看起来比实际情况更可怕
At the end of the day,
总之
I'd rather experience the Gs of Starship than the Gs of a Falcon 9 booster propulsive landing,
我宁愿体验Starship的过载 也不愿体验猎鹰9号助推器反推式着陆产生的过载
which pulls up to five Gs at certain points during re-entry and landing burns.
后者在再入大气层和着陆点火过程中的某些位置上会拉出高达5个G的过载
While that's certainly survivable, it's definitely starting to get pretty uncomfortable.
虽然这当然是可以承受的 但它肯定开始变得相当不舒服了
Now of course, no one's riding a Falcon 9 booster when it lands,
当然 没有人在猎鹰9号助推器着陆时乘坐它
but it just shows how high the G-forces are, in order to recover a booster vertically.
但数据就显示出了 为了垂直回收一个助推器 产生了多大的过载
So although the belly flop looks dangerous and nauseating,
因此 尽管机腹向下机动看起来很危险 令人恶心
it likely won't actually be that bad for humans.
但对载人来说 可能实际上并不那么糟糕
Especially if the seats compensated for the rotation,
特别是如果座椅对旋转进行了补偿
it'd probably be no big deal at all.
这可能根本就不是什么大问题
But as far as reliability, well only time will tell how reliable this actually can be.
但就可靠性而言 只有时间能证明这实际上有多可靠
So with that, I definitely think we need to wrap things up.
因此 我绝对认为我们需要把整件事进行总结
[bright music]
[欢快的音乐]
总结
So SpaceX is trying something pretty spectacular.
那么SpaceX正在尝试一些相当壮观的东西
And there's reasons to maybe be skeptical about it at this point, having seen so many failures
而在这一点上 也许有理由对它持怀疑态度 (毕竟)已经看到了这么多的失败案例
but let's not forget this is just the very beginning.
但我们不要忘记这只是一个开始
The Raptors aren't very mature yet either
这些猛禽发动机也还不是很成熟
and we'll definitely get more reliable, as they continue development.
而随着发动机的继续发展 肯定会变得更加可靠
For those of you that weren't around during the early days of the Falcon 9,
对于那些在猎鹰9号早期开发过程不甚了解的人来说
many people had their doubts that SpaceX could even get it to fly, ever.
许多人甚至怀疑SpaceX永远也不能让它飞起来
There were scrubs galore, problems and questions coming up every time they got a Falcon 9 to the pad.
每次他们把猎鹰9号运到发射台时 都会有大量的取消 问题和疑问出现
And then of course there many doubts, if they could ever get it to land.
之后当然也有很多人怀疑 他们是否能让它着陆
And at first it did seem like a bad idea and like something that just might never be worth their time.
而起初 这似乎是一个糟糕的想法 就像一个可能永远不值得他们花时间的东西
But now, no one doubts the merits of SpaceX landing and reusing their Falcon 9 boosters.
但现在 没有人怀疑SpaceX着陆和重复使用猎鹰9号助推器的好处
As of today about 75% of all Falcon 9 flights have successfully landed and been recovered.
截至今天 大约75%的猎鹰9号飞行已经成功着陆并被回收
And about half of all missions have been on re-flown boosters.
而所有任务中约有一半是使用重新飞行的助推器
They clearly have figured out a system that works incredibly well and has already changed the game.
很明显 他们已经研制出了一套高效的系统 并且已经改变了游戏规则
Or perhaps you remember when SpaceX started using super chill propellant for their Falcon 9.
或者你可能记得当SpaceX开始为他们的猎鹰9号使用过冷推进剂时
They were scrubbing constantly.
他们在不断地取消任务
For instance, SES-9, one of the first missions to use super chill props,
例如 首批使用过冷推进剂的任务之一 SES-9任务
was scrubbed four times because of issues with the super chilled propellant.
由于过冷推进剂的问题 该任务被取消了四次
And people were questioning, whether or not it was worth it
而人们在质疑 这是否值得
and if they could ever get it to actually just work out without being super finicky,
以及他们是否能让它真正发挥作用 而不是过分难用
including ULA's, Tory Bruno.
包括ULA的(CEO) Tory Bruno
But the ultimate question, why?
但本质上的问题是 为什么？
We've said it at the beginning and we'll say it again now that you understand everything.
我们在一开始就说过了 现在我们要再说一遍 因为你已经明白了一切
Using as much of the rocket to slow down in the atmosphere is possible, essentially for free,
让火箭尽可能多地在大气层中减速 不仅是行得通的 而且基本上是可以白用 的
that's a great reason right there.
这就是一个很好的理由
And then by doing the flip as late as possible,
然后通过尽可能晚地做翻转
they minimize gravity drag and they won't waste too much Delta V landing the rocket.
可以把重力拖拽(的损失)降到最低 使得火箭着陆不会浪费太多dv
In order to fulfill the goal of being a super heavy lift, fully reusable rocket,
为了使之成为一个超重型 完全可重复使用的运载火箭
they have to squeeze absolutely every little drop of performance out of the vehicle.
他们得从航天器中榨干每一滴性能
And the early days of this testing program, we're going to see a lot of failures.
而在这个测试项目的早期 我们会看到很多失败的情况
SpaceX will learn a lot of lessons but they're cranking these things out so fast,
SpaceX将学到很多教训 但他们生产这些东西的速度非常快
they can rapidly iterate and learn at a pace that will certainly lead to getting results in a hurry.
他们可以快速迭代并快速学习 而这肯定能在短时间内获得结果
But the reality is, I know the last minute aspect looks scary,
但现实是 我知道最后一分钟看起来很可怕
but frankly every part just simply needs to work.
但坦率地说 每个部分都只是简单地需要能起作用
This all just needs to become more reliable period.
而这一切真的只是需要变得更加可靠
And if I know anything about SpaceX, they will force this thing into being reliable
而如果说我知道SpaceX的什么事情 那就是他们将迫使这东西变得可靠
because they don't seem to take no for an answer.
因为他们似乎不接受放弃的答案
After all nothing that's physically possible is impossible.
毕竟物理上可能的 总是能行得通的
But at the end of the day,
但总之
who knows, SpaceX could play around with this for a while and then say, "You know what?
谁知道呢 SpaceX可能会这样玩一段时间 然后说 你知道吗？
Let's just focus on what gets us the absolute highest chances of safely landing and recovering period."
让我们专注于绝对最安全的着陆和回收
And then they could make some just drastic changes.
然后这样他们就会做出一些巨大的改变
I mean, Elon's already talking about catching the booster with the launch tower
我是指 马一龙已经在谈论用发射塔接住助推器了
and maybe even doing that same thing with Starship.
同时甚至可能对Starship做同样的事情
Who knows, maybe someday we'll see them blowing a bunch of fans up at Starship and catching it in a giant net.
谁知道呢 也许有一天我们会看到他们在Starship上展开一堆风扇 然后用一张巨大的网把它抓住
I mean, I feel like nothing is off the table for SpaceX,
我是指 我觉得对SpaceX来说没有什么是不可能的
but for now I'm excited to see them try this more
但现在我很高兴看到他们对现有的Starship方案进行更多尝试
because it sure is exciting.
因为这肯定是令人兴奋的
So what do you think?
那么 你怎么看
Do you think SpaceX will figure out this maneuver and make it reliable and routine?
Or do you think they'll wind up back at the drawing board
and have to come up with another completely different solution altogether?
Let me know your thoughts in the comments below.
I owe a quick thank you to a lot of people who helped make this video possible,
including Declan Murphy from flightclub.io.
You guys should definitely be familiar with this,
if you're out ever trying to take pictures of a rocket,
be sure and check out his rocket photographer toolkit.
There's a ton of really fun stuff to play with though, too.
So definitely check out flightclub.io.
It is awesome and Declan does amazing work and check him out on YouTube too,
cause he's doing an awesome job explaining some of the differences we're seeing between these missions.
And also Casper Stanley,
who made a lot of the awesome 3D renders in this video,
check out his rocket Explorer app on the steam store,
which is super cool.
And another thanks to Corey @C_bass3d on Twitter,
for some of his incredible animations as well.
And a lot of the footage you saw from this video was from the partnership I have
with my friends at Cosmic Perspective.
So Ryan Shilanski and Mary Liz Bender,
who worked with me to make a lot of the incredible video that you see on launch day.
Definitely watch their incredible films on YouTube,
find their YouTube page right now.
And once you watch their videos,
I can just about guarantee you're going to want to support them.
So you get some awesome access to behind the scenes stuff and help them continue to do what they do,
by going to patreon.com/cosmicperspective.
But I owe a huge thank you to my Patreon supporters,
who helped make this video,
Mars studio B and everything that we do at Everyday Astronaut possible.
So if you want to help support what I do or gain access to our incredible discord community,
who is just the most fun audience to be with on launch day or just hang out during the week,
asking people rocket questions and stuff like that.
Or if you want to get access to some exclusive live streams as well,
consider becoming a Patreon supporter by going to patreon.com/everydayastronaut.
And while you're online, definitely check out our awesome web store for shirts like this shirt,
that I'm sure you've seen many times.
This is the full flow stage combustion cycle shirt,
that of course you've probably seen Elon Musk wear or his baby or whoever elsewhere, it's an awesome shirt.
All of our merch is the highest quality possible by screen printing them.
And we just do bulk orders of merchandise,
it's not print on demand stuff that will fall apart after three times wearing it.
So definitely check out, shop around,
find some awesome stuff for you or some friends,
by going to everyday astronaut.com/shop.
Thanks everybody. That's going to do it for me.
谢谢大家观看 本期节目到这里就结束了
I'm Tim Dodd, the everyday astronaut,
我是Tim Dodd 每日宇航员
bringing space down to Earth, for everyday people.
将太空的知识带给地球上的普通人
[bright music]
[欢快的音乐]